<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
	<!-- References are listed here so that they can be called via Entity attributes later -->
		<!ENTITY RFC1034 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1034.xml">
		<!ENTITY RFC1035 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1035.xml">
		<!ENTITY RFC4033 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4033.xml">
		<!ENTITY RFC4034 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4034.xml">
		<!ENTITY RFC4035 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4035.xml">
		<!ENTITY RFC4398 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4398.xml">
		<!ENTITY RFC4509 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4509.xml">
		<!ENTITY RFC5155 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5155.xml">
		<!ENTITY RFC5914 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5914.xml">
		<!ENTITY RFC6781 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6781.xml">
		<!ENTITY RFC7646 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7646.xml">
		<!ENTITY I-D.draft-livingood-dnsop-dont-switch-resolvers SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-livingood-dnsop-dont-switch-resolvers-03.xml">
		]>
		
			 
		<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
			
			
		<!-- PROCESSING INSTRUCTIONS - GENERAL -->
		<!-- EACH ONE STARTS WITH '?' BELOW -->
		
		<!-- give errors on I-D nits and perform DTD validation -->
		<!-- control the table of contents (ToC) -->
		<?rfc strict='yes' ?>
		
		<?rfc toc='yes'?>
		<!-- generate a ToC -->

		<!-- the number of levels of subsections in ToC. default: 3 -->
		<?rfc tocdepth='4'?>
		
		<!-- END GENERAL PROCESSING -->
		
		<!-- PROCESSING INSTRUCTIONS - CONTROL OF REFERENCES -->
		
		<!-- use symbolic references tags, i.e, [RFC2119] instead of [1] -->
		<?rfc symrefs='yes'?>
		
		<!-- sort the reference entries alphabetically -->
		<!-- control vertical white space -->
		<?rfc sortrefs='yes' ?>
		
		<!-- do not start each main section on a new page -->
		<?rfc compact='yes' ?>
				
		<!-- keep one blank line between list items -->
		<?rfc subcompact='no' ?>
		
		<!-- END REFERENCE PROCESSING -->
		
    <rfc ipr='trust200902' docName='draft-livingood-dnsop-auth-dnssec-mistakes-03' category='info'>
  	<!-- category values: std, bcp, info, exp, and historic
     ipr values: full3978, noModification3978, noDerivatives3978
     you can add the attributes updates="NNNN" and obsoletes="NNNN" 
     they will automatically be output with "(if approved)" -->
		
			<!-- FRONT SECTION -->
    	<front>
				<title abbrev='Responsibility for DNSSEC Mistakes'>
				Responsibility for Authoritative DNS and DNSSEC Mistakes 
				</title>
				
		    <!-- add role='editor' attribute to author tag below for the editors if appropriate -->
		    		

        		<author initials='J.' surname='Livingood' fullname='Jason Livingood'>
					<organization abbrev='Comcast'>
					Comcast 
					</organization>
					<address>
						<postal>
        					<city>Philadelphia</city> 
        					<country>US</country>
						</postal>
    					<email>jason_livingood@comcast.com</email>
    					<uri>http://www.comcast.com</uri>
					</address>
				<!-- author role='editor' is an optional value here -->
				</author>
				
				
        	<date day='18' month='February' year='2019'/>
				
			<!-- META-DATA DECLARATIONS -->
    		<area>Operations and Management Area</area>
				
			<!-- WG name at the upperleft corner of the doc; 'Internet Engineering Task Force' 
			is fine for individual submissions.  -->
    		<workgroup>Domain Name System Operations</workgroup>
    
		    <!-- Keywords will be incorporated into HTML output files in a meta tag but they 
			have no effect on text or nroff output. If you submit your draft to the RFC Editor, 
			the keywords will be used for the search engine. -->
			
			<keyword>RFC</keyword>
			<keyword>Request for Comments</keyword>
			<keyword>I-D</keyword>
			<keyword>Internet-Draft</keyword>
    			<keyword>Comcast</keyword>
    			<keyword>ISP</keyword>
    			<keyword>Internet Service Provider</keyword>
    			<keyword>DNS</keyword>
    			<keyword>DNSSEC</keyword>
    			<keyword>Negative Trust Anchors</keyword>
				
        	<abstract>
        	<t>DNS Security Extensions (DNSSEC) validation by recursive DNS resolvers has been deployed 
			at scale. However, domain signing tools and processes are not yet as mature and 
			reliable as is the case for non-DNSSEC-related domain administration tools and 
			processes. This sometimes results in DNSSEC-validation failures, for which 
			operators of validating resolvers are often blamed. This is similar to other, 
			non-DNSSEC-related authoritative DNS errors, for which individual recursive DNS 
			operators are sometimes incorrectly blamed. This document makes clear that 
			responsibility for any and all authoritative DNS failures rests squarely with 
			authoritative domain name operators, who are the only party that can 
			properly maintain their domain names and rectify associated authoritative DNS errors.</t>
				
    		</abstract>
			
			<!-- END META-DATA DECLARATIONS -->

			</front>
			<!-- END FRONT SECTION -->
			
			<!-- MIDDLE SECTION -->
			<middle>

			<section anchor='intro' title='Introduction' toc='include'>
				
			<t>The Domain Name System (DNS), DNS Security Extensions (DNSSEC), and related operational 
				practices are defined extensively <xref target='RFC1034'/> <xref target='RFC1035'/> 
				<xref target='RFC4033'/> <xref target='RFC4034'/> <xref target='RFC4035'/> 
				<xref target='RFC4398'/> <xref target='RFC4509'/> <xref target='RFC6781'/> 
				<xref target='RFC5155'/>.</t>
								
			<t>DNS Security Extensions (DNSSEC) validation by recursive DNS resolvers has been deployed 
			at scale. However, domain signing tools and processes are not yet as mature and 
			reliable as is the case for non-DNSSEC-related domain administration tools and 
			processes. This sometimes results in DNSSEC-validation failures, for which 
			operators of validating resolvers are often blamed. This is similar to other, 
			non-DNSSEC-related authoritative DNS errors, for which individual recursive DNS 
			operators are sometimes incorrectly blamed. This documents makes clear that 
			responsibility for any and all authoritative DNS failures rests squarely with 
			authoritative domain name operators, who are the only party that can 
			properly maintain their domain names and rectify associated authoritative DNS errors.</t>
				
			<t>Operators of DNS recursive resolvers, including Internet Service Providers (ISPs) and 
				cloud-based DNS resolvers, occasionally observe domains incorrectly managing 
				DNSSEC-related resource records. This mismanagement triggers DNSSEC validation failures, 
				and then causes large numbers of end users to be unable to reach a domain.
				Similarly, errors in non-DNSSEC-related authoritative DNS resource records result in 
				failures, from NXDOMAIN responses to valid responses containing outdated 
				or unreachable hosts. </t> 
				
			<t>Many end users, as well as reporters, policymakers, regulators, and others often 
				interpret this as a failure of particular recursive DNS resolvers. Rather than seeing this as 
				a failure on the part of the domain they wanted to reach, they may themselves 
				and/or recommend to others that they switch to a 
				non-validating resolver (which reduces their security), switch to a different DNS 
				resolver (which can reduce non-DNS application layer performance), or contact their 
				ISP or DNS resolver operator to complain.</t>
				
			<t>This document makes clear, however, that responsibility for these types of 
				authoritative DNS failures rests squarely 
				with authoritative domain name operators, as noted in 
				<xref target='Responsibility-for-Failures'/>.</t>
				
			</section>
			
			<section title='Domain Validation Failures' anchor='Domain-Validation-Failures' toc='include'>
			<t>A domain name can fail validation for two general reasons, a legitimate security failure such 
				as due to an attack or compromise of some sort, or as a result of misconfiguration or 
				other error or omission on 
				the part of an domain administrator. As domains transition to DNSSEC the most likely 
				reason for a validation failure during and shortly after the transition is likely due 
				to misconfiguration. Thus, domain 
				administrators should be sure to read <xref target="RFC6781"/> in full. They should also 
				pay special attention to Section 4.2, pertaining to key rollovers, which appears to be the 
				cause of many validation failures.</t>
			
			<t>In one example <xref target="DNSSEC-Validation-Failure-Analysis"/>, a specific domain 
				name failed to validate. An investigation revealed that the domain's administrators 
				performed a Key Signing Key (KSK) rollover by (1) generating a new key and (2) signing 
				the domain with the new key. However, they did not use a double-signing procedure for the 
				KSK and a pre-publish procedure for the ZSK. Double-signing refers to signing a zone with 
				two KSKs and then updating the parent zone with the new DS record so that both keys are 
				valid at the same time. This meant that the domain name was signed with the new KSK, but 
				it was not double-signed with the old KSK. So, the new key was used for signing the zone 
				but the old key was not. As a result, the domain could not be trusted and returned an error 
				when trying to reach the domain. Thus, the domain was in a situation where the DNSSEC 
				chain of trust was broken because the Delegation Signer (DS) record pointed to the old 
				KSK, which was no longer used for signing the zone. (A DS record provides a link in 
				the chain of trust for DNSSEC from the parent zone to the child zone - in this case 
				between TLD and domain name.)</t> 
				
			<t>In a non-DNSSEC-related example, a domain administrator may add a new host with an A and AAAA 
				resource record pointing the name to the IP addresses of new servers with a Time To Live 
				(TTL) of two days. But they may turn down the old servers with a similar two day TTL 
				before that TTL has expired. As a result, some number of users are likely to 
				continue to attempt to connect to the old IP addresses that are no longer reachable. 
				While a best practice is to reduce the TTL to a matter of seconds or minutes before 
				such a shift, many domains continue to forget the impact that the TTL can have, or 
				make countless other errors in ther domain name, server, and network administration 
				that negatively impacts domain name-based reachability.</t>
			
			</section>
            
            <section title='Responsibility for Failures' anchor='Responsibility-for-Failures' toc='include'>
			<t>An authoritative domain owner is solely and completely responsible for 
				managing their domain name(s) and associated DNS resource records. 
				This includes complete responsibility for the correctness of those resource 
				records, the proper functioning and reachability of their 
				authoritative DNS servers, and the correctness of DNS records linking their domain 
				to a top-level domain (TLD) or other higher level domain. The domain owner is also 
				responsible for selection of the authoritative domain administrator, operator, or 
				service provider. Thus, even in cases where some error may be introduced by a third 
				party, whether that is due to an authoritative server software vendor, software 
				tools vendor, domain name registrar, Content Delivery Network (CDN), or other 
				organization, these are all parties 
				that the domain owner has selected and is responsible for managing 
				successfully.</t>
			
			<t>There are some cases where the domain administrator is different than the domain owner. 
				In those cases, a domain owner has delegated operational responsibility to the 
				domain administrator (and that domain administrator may further delegate 
				some sub-domains and/or records to another party, such as a CDN). So no matter 
				whether a domain owner is also the domain administrator or not, the domain owner 
				and domain administrator are nevertheless operationally responsible for the 
				proper configuration and operation of the domain name .</t>
			
			<t>In the case of a domain name failing DNSSEC validation, even when this is due to 
				a misconfiguration of the domain, that is the sole responsibility of the domain 
				owner.</t>
			
			<t>Any assistance or mitigation responses undertaken by other parties to mitigate the 
				misconfiguration of a domain name by a domain owner and/or administrator, especially operators 
				of DNS recursive resolvers, are optional and at the pleasure of those parties. This can 
		    		the use of a Negative Trust Anchor <xref="RFC7646"/> and/or clearing the 
		    		cache in particular DNS resolvers.</t>
            </section>
            
            <section title='Comparison to Other DNS Misconfigurations' anchor='Comparison-to-Other-DNS-Misconfigurations' toc='include'>
			<t>As noted in <xref target="Responsibility-for-Failures"/> domain administrators are 
				ultimately responsible for managing and ensuring their DNS records are configured 
				correctly. ISPs or other DNS recursive resolver operators cannot and should not 
				correct misconfigured A, CNAME, MX, or other resource records of domains for 
				which they are not authoritative. Expecting non-authoritative entities to protect 
				domain owners and administrators from any misconfiguration of resource records 
				is therefore unrealistic and unreasonable, does not scale well, and is strongly 
				contrary to the delegated design of the DNS and could lead to extensive 
				operational instability and/or variation.</t>
            </section>
            
            <section title='Other Considerations' anchor='Other-Considerations' toc='include'>
           		
           		<section title='Security Considerations' anchor='Security-Considerations' toc='include'>
            	<t>Authoritative domain name owners and/or administrators, in the case of DNSSEC-related 
			mistakes that cause validation failures to occur, should focus on correcting the 
			issue and then improving their processes and tools in the future. During the period of 
			time that their domain cannot be resolved due to a DNSSEC-related mistake, they SHOULD NOT  
			encourage end users to switch to non-validating resolvers, as the use of a non-validating 
			DNS recursive resolver has comparatively less security capabilities than a validating 
			resolver, since one implements DNS Security Extensions and one does not. In addition, 
			if an end user changes to a non-validating resolver they may subject themselves to 
			increased security risks and threats against which DNS Security Extensions may have 
			provided protection.</t>
    			</section>
            	
            	<section title='Privacy Considerations' anchor='Privacy-Considerations' toc='include'>
            	<t>There are no privacy considerations in this document.</t>
            	</section>
            	
            	<section title='IANA Considerations' anchor='IANA-Considerations' toc='include'>
            	<t>There are no IANA considerations in this document.</t>
        		</section>
           	</section>
            
			<section title='Acknowledgements' toc='include'>
        	<t>- William Brown</t>
      		</section>	
		
		
		</middle>
		<!-- END MIDDLE SECTION -->
			
		<!-- BACK SECTION -->
		<back>
			
			<references title='Normative References'>
				&RFC1034;
				&RFC1035;
				&RFC4033;
				&RFC4034;
				&RFC4035;
				&RFC4398;
				&RFC4509;
				&RFC5155;
				&RFC5914;
				&RFC6781;
				&RFC7646;
			</references>
			
			<references title='Informative References'>
				
				
				
				&I-D.draft-livingood-dnsop-dont-switch-resolvers;
			
					<reference anchor="DNSSEC-Validation-Failure-Analysis" target="http://www.dnssec.comcast.net/DNSSEC_Validation_Failure_NASAGOV_20120118_FINAL.pdf">
       					<front>
            				<title>Analysis of DNSSEC Validation Failure - NASA.GOV</title>   
            				<author initials='J.' surname='Barnitz' fullname='John Barnitz'>
            				<organization abbrev='Comcast'>Comcast</organization>
            				</author>  		
            				<author initials='T.' surname='Creighton' fullname='Tom Creighton'>
            				<organization abbrev='Comcast'>Comcast</organization>
            				</author>  			
            				<author initials='C.' surname='Ganster' fullname='Chris Ganster'>
            				<organization abbrev='Comcast'>Comcast</organization>
            				</author>  			
            				<author initials='C.' surname='Griffiths' fullname='Chris Griffiths'>
            				<organization abbrev='Comcast'>Comcast</organization>
            				</author>  			
            				<author initials='J.' surname='Livingood' fullname='Jason Livingood'>
            				<organization abbrev='Comcast'>Comcast</organization>
            				</author>  				
            				<date month="January" day="24" year="2012"/>
        				</front>
        				<seriesInfo name="Comcast" value=""/>  
    				</reference>

    		</references>
			
            
		<section title='Document Change Log'>
	 		<t>[RFC Editor: This section is to be removed before publication]</t>
     		<t>Individual-00: First version published as an individual draft.</t>
     		<t>Individual-01: Fixed nits identified by William Brown</t>
     		<t>Individual-02: Updated prior to IETF-91</t>
     		<t>WG-00: Renamed at request of DNSOP co-chairs</t>
     		<t>WG-01: Updated doc to keep it from expiring</t>
     		<t>WG-02: Removed RFC 2119 reference in XML</t>
     		<t>WG-03: Refreshed draft and broadened to all auth issues, not just DNSSEC.</t>
		</section>

		<section title='Open Issues'>
			<t>[RFC Editor: This section is to be removed before publication]</t>
			<t>No open issues at this time</t>
		</section>

	</back>
	<!-- END BACK SECTION -->

    </rfc>

		
		<!-- FOR REFERENCE -->
		<!-- less than is &lt -->
		<!-- ampersand is &amp -->
		<!-- apostrophe is &apos -->
		<!-- quotation is &quot -->
